Guide to the Varian Fry Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Varian Fry Papers,
[ca. 1940]-1967
Fry, Varian, 1907-1967.
9 linear ft. (ca.3,000 items in 19 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4078792
Biographical Note
Fry, a 32 year old Harvard-educated classicist and editor from New York City, helped save thousands of endangered refugees who were caught in the Vichy French area during World War II. His efforts saved prominent persons: Max Ernst; Marc Chagall; Hannah Arendt; Andre Breton; Marcel Duchamp; Franz Werfel; Jacques Lipchitz; Lion Feuchtwanger; Heinrich Mann; Hans Sahl; Wilfredo Lam; Walter Mehring; Otto Meyerhoff; and Alma Mahler. In total, Fry and his collaborators helped to save around 4,000 people. In 1991, 24 years after his death (1967) in obscurity, Fry received his first official recognition from a United States agency, the United States Holocaust Memorial Council. In 1996, Varian Mackey Fry was named as "Righteous Among the Nations" by Yad Vashem, the Holocaust Heros and Martyrs Remembrance Authority in Jerusalem. He was the first American recipient of Israel's highest honor for rescuers during the Holocaust. After the war, Fry wrote a memoir of his days in marseilles, "Assignment Rescue". The FBI kept a file on him throughout his life, viewing his activities with some suspicion.
Scope and Content
The collection includes the original manuscript of "Surrender on Demand", Mr. Fry's account of his wartime experiences, which was later rewritten for young readers as "Assignment Rescue" (New York, Four Winds Press, 1968). Among the correspondents represented in the collection are Marc Chagall, Jacques Lipchitz, Roger Baldwin, Norman Thomas, J. Edgar Hoover, and Herman Wouk. In addition to the material relating to the Emergency Relief Committee (later known as the International Rescue Committee), the collection includes correspondence and papers concerning Fry's work as a writer on foreign affairs as well as copies of his books.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 9 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Personal Correspondence
Series IV: Subject Files
Series V: Manuscripts
Series VI: Photographs
Series VII: Printed Material
Series VIII: 2004 Addition
Series IX: 2005 Addition
Subjects
Emergency Rescue Committee.; International Rescue Committee.; United States.--Congress.--House.--Committee on Un-American Activities.; Baldwin, Roger N. (Roger Nash), 1884-1981.; Chagall, Marc, 1887-1985.; Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968.; Ernst, Max, 1891-1976.; Gide, André, 1869-1951.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Kinsey, Alfred C. (Alfred Charles), 1894-1956.; Komroff, Manuel, 1890-1974.; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-1973.; Macdonald, Dwight.; Malraux, André, 1901-1976.; Matisse, Henri, 1869-1954.; Miró, Joan, 1893-1983.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968.; Winter, Ella.; Wouk, Herman, 1915-; France--History--German occupation, 1940-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Concentration camps.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945--War work.; Refugees--France.; Articles.; Audio tapes.; Bibliographies.; Lists.; Manuscripts (literary).; Maps.; Notes.; Passports.; Photographs.; Photonegatives.; Receipts.; Reports.; Reviews.; Songs.; Tax returns.; Visas.; Authors.; Editors.; Foreign agents.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1969 M-69 Fry, Mrs. Varian Gift
Gift of Annette Riley Fry, 1969 & 1974.
Related Material
Fry's letters to Daniel Benedite, 1941-1955, are in the Friedrich Ebert Foundation, 5300 Bonn 2, Godesberger Allee 149, Germany.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Baldwin, Roger Nash (Box 1)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2015]
  - Chagall, Marc (Box 1)
  - Duchamp, Marcel (Box 1)
  - Ernst, Max (Box 1)
  - Gide, Andre (Box 1)
  - Guerard, Albert (Box 1)
  - Hoover, J. Edgar (Box 1)
  - Kinsey, Alfred C. (Box 1)
  - Komroff (Box 1)
  - Lipchitz, Jacques (Box 1)
  - MacDonald, Dwight (Box 1)
  - Malraux, Andre (Box 1)
  - Matisse, Henri (Box 1)
  - Miro, Joan (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Box 1)
  - Thomas, Norman (Box 1)
  - Winter, Ella (Box 1)
  - Wouk, Herman (Box 1)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  Box 2 is on microfilm MN#2000-2015 & 2016
  - Allen, Jay (Box 2)
  - Arp, Jean (Box 2)
  - Ascoli, Max (Box 2)
  - Bacon, Francis (Box 2)
  - Baskin, Leonard (Box 2)
  - Barde, Simone (Box 2)
  - Benda, Julien (Box 2)
  - Benedite, Daniel, Aug.-Dec. 1941 Jan.-May 1942 (Box 2)
  - Benedite, Daniel, June - Nov. 1942 -- Oct. 1943 - Mar. 1945 -- Apr. 1945 - Apr. 1946 -- 1955 - 1966 -- Aug.-Dec. 1941 [Duplicates] -- Jan. - May 1942 [Duplicates] -- June-Nov. 1942 [Duplicates] -- Dec. 1944 [Duplicates] (Box 2)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2016]
  - Benedite, Theodora (Box 3)
  - Berman, Eugene (Box 3)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2017]
  - Brauner, Voctor (Box 3)
  - Breitscheid, Rudolf (Box 3)
  - Breton, Andre and Jacqueline (Box 3)
  - Calder, Alexander (Box 3)
  - Campigli, Massimo (Box 3)
  - Cardazzo, Renato (Box 3)
  - Chagall, Marc (Box 3)
  - Chagall, V. (Box 3)
  - Davenport, Miriam (Box 3)
  - Da Silva, Viera (Box 3)
  - De Segonzac, Andre Dunoyer (Box 3)
  - Dubuffet, Jean (Box 3)
  - Duchamp, Marcel (Box 3)
  - Ehrmann, Henry and Claire (Box 3)
  - Elbogen, Paul (Box 3)
  - Ernst, Max (Box 3)
  - Fawcett, Charles (Box 3)
  - Feininger, Lionel (Box 3)
  - Feuchtwanger, Lion (Box 3)
  - Fischmann, Lena (Box 3)
  - Filtko, Johannes (Box 3)
  - Freier, Bill (Box 3)
  - Friedlander, Paul (Box 3)
  - Frucht, Carl (Box 3)
  - Fry, Annette (Box 3)
  - Fry, Arthur (Box 3)
  - Fry, Eileen, Aug. 1940 - Feb. 1941 Mar. 1941 - Oct. 1941 Undated (period Aug. 1940 - Aug. 1941) (Box 3)
  - Fry, Lillian (Box 3)
  - Gemahling, Jean (Box 4)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2018]
  - Giacometti, Alberto (Box 4)
  - Glauber, Henry (Box 4)
  - Gold, Mary Jayne (Box 4)
  - Gruss, Anna (Box 4)
  - Guggenheim, Peggy (Box 4)
  - Heiden, Konrad (Box 4)
  - Heilbut, Ivan (Box 4)
  - Heine, Fritz (Box 4)
  - Heppner, Sam (Box 4)
  - Hewson, Manning (Box 4)
  - Hilb, E. (Box 4)
  - Hilferding, Rudolph (Box 4)
  - Hirschman, Albert (Box 4)
  - Jacob, Berthold (Box 4)
  - Jay, Charles R. (Box 4)
  - Kingdon, Frank (Box 4)
  - Kirchway, Freda (Box 4)
  - Kokoschka, Oskar (Box 4)
  - Lam, Wilfredo (Box 4)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2019]
  - Lamm, Fritz (Box 4)
  - Lewis, Flora (Box 4)
  - Lipchitz, Jacques (Box 4)
  - Lusso, Emilio (Box 4)
  - Malraux, Andre (Box 4)
  - Mann, Golo (Box 4)
  - Marini, Marino (Box 4)
  - Masson, Andre (Box 4)
  - Matisse, Henri (Box 4)
  - Mehring, Walter (Box 4)
  - Meyerhoff, Otto (Box 4)
  - Miro, Jean (Box 4)
  - Modigliani, Giuseppe (Box 4)
  - Moore, Henry (Box 4)
  - Natonek, Hans (Box 5)
  - Oppenheimer, Heinz Ernest (Box 5)
  - Oram, Harold (Box 5)
  - Pauli, Hertha (Box 5)
  - Picasso, Pablo (Box 5)
  - Pignon, Edouard (Box 5)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Box 5)
  - Roumilhac, Jean (Box 5)
  - Sahl, Hans (Box 5)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2020]
  - Serge, Victor (Box 5)
  - Spiro, Eugen (Box 5)
  - Super, Yvan (Box 5)
  - Sutherland, Graham (Box 5)
  - Van Dongen (Box 5)
  - Verdet, Andre (Box 5)
  - Verzeano, Marcel (Box 5)
  - Vochoc, Vladimir (Box 5)
  - Von Hildebrand, Franz (Box 5)
  - Vortriede, Werner (Box 5)
  - Warbura, Ingrid (Box 5)
  - Weisslitz, Jacques (Box 5)
  - Werfel, Franz and Alma mahler (Box 5)
  - Wolff, Margot (Box 5)
  - Wyman, David S. (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Series III: Personal Correspondence
  - Brown, Robert M. (Box 6)
  - "C" (Box 6)
  - "D" (Box 6)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2021]
  - "E" (Box 6)
  - "F" (Box 6)
  - Fry, Eileen, 1932 (Box 6)
  - "G" (Box 6)
  - "H" (Box 6)
  - "I" (Box 6)
  - "J" (Box 6)
  - "K" (Box 6)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2022]
  - "L" (Box 6)
  - Leigh, W. Colston (Box 6)
  - Liebert, Michael (Box 6)
  - "M" (Box 6)
  - Meistermann, Georg (Box 6)
  - "N" (Box 6)
  - Noggle, John R. (Box 6)
  - "O" (Box 6)
  - "P" (Box 6)
  - "Q" (Box 6)
  - "R" (Box 6)
  - "S" (Box 6)
  - "T" (Box 6)
  - "U" (Box 6)
  - "V" (Box 6)
  - "W" (Box 6)
  - "XYZ" (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Series IV: Subject Files
  - Advertising (Box 7)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2023]
  - American China Policy Association (Box 7)
  - American Committee for Cultural Freedom (Box 7)
  - American Consulates in Europe (Box 7)
  - American Embassy, Vichy (Box 7)
  - Art, Commission Sales of (Box 7)
  - Art Work, Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Benedite, Daniel, Articles (Box 7)
  - Breitscheid and Hilferding (Box 7)
  - Caballero, Largo (Box 7)
  - Censorship (Box 7)
  - Centre Americain de Secours Adminstrative Reports (1 of 2) (Box 7)
  - Centre Americain de Secours Adminstrative Reports [2 of 2] (Box 7)
  - Centre Americain de Secours Files, Location of (Box 7)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2024]
  - Centre Americain de Secours Financial Reports (Box 7)
  - Centre Americain de Secours Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Centre Americain de Secours Notes and Chronologies, Varian Fry (Box 7)
  - Centre Americain de Secours Staff (Box 7)
  - Chronology, 1940 (Box 8)
  - Columbia University (Box 8)
  - "Common Sense" (Box 8)
  - Varian Fry Curriculum Vitae (Box 8)
  - Customs Declarations (Box 8)
  - Dohrn, Klaus (Box 8)
  - Varian Fry Duties, Marseille (Box 8)
  - Edizione del Cinquale (cross ref. "Flight Portfolio") (Box 8)
  - Emergency Rescue Committee (Box 8)
  - Ephemera (Box 8)
  - Expenses, Return from Marseille (Box 8)
  - Expulsion from France, 1941 (Box 8)
  - Ferro, Antonio (Box 8)
  - Flight Portfolio, (1 of 3 ) (Box 8)
  - Flight Portfolio, (2 of 3 ) (Box 8)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2025]
  - Flight Portfolio, (3 of 3 ) (Box 8)
  - Foreign Policy Association (Box 8)
  - Fry, Varian Article on ERC, 1965, (2 folders ) (Box 8)
  - Gide, Andre (Box 8)
  - Gold, Mary Jayne "Muller's Escape", (1 Audio tape recording ) (Box 8)
  - House Un-American Committee, 1951- 55, (1 of 2 ) (Box 9)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2026]
  - House Un-American Committee, 1951- 55, (2 of 2 ) (Box 9)
  - Income Tax, 1934 (Box 9)
  - Income Tax, 1935 (Box 9)
  - Income Tax, 1936 (Box 9)
  - Income Tax, 1937 (Box 9)
  - Income Tax, 1938 (Box 9)
  - Income Tax, 1939 (Box 9)
  - Income Tax, 1940 (Box 9)
  - Income Tax, 1941 (Box 9)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2027]
  - Income Tax, 1942 (Box 9)
  - Income Tax, 1943 (Box 9)
  - Income Tax, 1944 (Box 9)
  - Income Tax, General (Box 9)
  - International League for the Rights of Man (Box 9)
  - International Rescue Committee (Box 9)
  - International Awards Committee Awards Luncheon, 1963 (Box 9)
  - Internment Camps, (1 of 3 ) (Box 9)
  - Internment Camps, (2 of 3 ) (Box 9)
  - Internment Camps, (3 of 3 ) (Box 9)
  - Internment Camps, Boegler and Lamm in Vernet (Box 10)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2028]
  - Internment Camps, Children in (Box 10)
  - "Italy Against Fascism" (Box 10)
  - Joy, Charles R. (Box 10)
  - Lam, Wilfredo (Box 10)
  - Legion d'Honneur (Box 10)
  - Lyon (Box 10)
  - Malaquais, Jean "Les Hors La Loi" (Box 10)
  - Maps (Box 10)
  - Maritain, Jacques (Box 10)
  - Marseille, Preparation to Depart for (Box 10)
  - Montauban Cases (Box 10)
  - New School for Social Research (Box 10)
  - Organizations Of Which Fry Was A Member (Box 10)
  - Passport, Correspondence (Box 10)
  - Personal Memorabilia (Box 10)
  - Photographs, Varian Fry, notes (Box 10)
  - Receipts, 1939-1941 (Box 10)
  - Receipts, 1966 (Box 10)
  - Refugees (Box 10)
  - Refugees, Lists of Endangered, 1941 (Box 10)
  - Refugees, Spanish (Box 10)
  - Secret Routes,France and Spain (Box 10)
  - Sinaia, Varian Fry's Arrest (Box 10)
  - Songs, French (Box 10)
    [On microfilm MN#2000-2029]
  - Songs, Portuguese (Box 10)
  - Varian Fry Speaking Engagements (Box 10)
  - Special Committe in Relief of Political Refugees, Proposed Members (Box 10)
  - Spiro, Eugen (Box 10)
  - Tailors (Box 10)
  - Unitarian Service Committee (Box 10)
  - United Nations Organization, (2 folders ) (Box 10)
  - Victor, Walther (Box 10)
  - Visas (Box 10)
  - Vochoc, Vladimir (Box 10)
  - Wartime Organizations (Box 10)
  - YMCA (Box 10)
  - Varian Fry Youth (Box 10)
- Series V: Manuscripts
  - Subseries V.1: Surrender on Demand
    - Jacket (Box 11)
      [On microfilm MN#2000-2066]
    - Notes, (1 of 2 ) (Box 11)
    - Notes, (2 of 2 ) (Box 11)
    - "A Day in the Lift of Rue Grignon # 60" (Box 11)
      [On microfilm MN#2000-2066 On microfilm MN#2000-2066]
    - Operation Emergency Rescue Publication Notes. (Box 11)
    - Reviews, (1 of 2 ) (Box 11)
    - Reviews, (2 of 2 ) (Box 11)
    - Manuscript 1, Forward (Box 11)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 1 (Box 11)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 2A (Box 11)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 2B (Box 11)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 3A (Box 11)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 3B (Box 11)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 4 (Box 11)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 5 (Box 11)
      [On microfilm MN#2000-2067]
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 8A (Box 12)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 8B (Box 12)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 9 (Box 12)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 10 (Box 12)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 11 (Box 12)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 12 (Box 12)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 13 (Box 12)
    - Manuscript 1, Chapter 14 (Box 12)
    - "If you enter..." "Un nomme Guerard..." "At Port Bou..." "These we saved..." Insertions (Box 12)
    - Manuscript 2: 1-80 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript 2: 81-180 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript 2: 181-209 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript 2: 270-349 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript 2: 350-450 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript 2: 461-560 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      [On microfilm MN#2000-2069]
    - Manuscript 2: 561-661 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript 2: 662-790 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Typescript: Front Matter Chapter 1 Chapter 2 Chapter 3 Chapter 4 Chapter 5 Chapter 6 Chapter 7 Chapter 8 Chapter 9 Chapter 10 Chapter 11 Chapter 12 Chapter 13 Chapter 14 Chapter 15 Epilogue Insertions and Replacement Pages (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous: Omitted pages: 1-6 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous: Manuscript pages: 1 Manuscript pages: 2A and 2B Manuscript pages: 3A and 3B Manuscript pages: 4A, 4B, 4C Lisbon Trip, 1940 (Box 15)
- Series VI: Photographs
  - Follow the link on the left to see a list of the photographs. (Box 16 & 16A)
- Series VII: Printed Material
  - Anti-Nazi Prisoners (Box 17)
  - Art, Sale of (Box 17)
  - Artists and Writers, Miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - "Austrian Labor News" (Box 17)
  - Baer, Martin (Box 17)
  - "La Bataille de la Grande-Bretagne" (Box 17)
  - Bernhard, Georg (Box 17)
  - Breitscheid and Hilferding (Box 17)
  - Breton, Andre (Box 17)
  - Caballero, Largo (Box 17)
  - Clader, Alexander (Box 17)
  - Chagall, Marc (Box 17)
  - Clippings, Miscellaneous, (1 of 2 ) (Box 17)
  - Clippings, Miscellaneous (2 of 2) (Box 17)
  - De Segonzac, Andre Dunoyer (Box 17)
  - De Thierrens, Favre (Box 17)
  - Europe, World War II, General (Box 17)
  - Fawcett, Charles (Box 17)
  - Feuchtwanger, Lion (Box 17)
  - Frank, Karl (Paul Hagen) (Box 17)
  - Fry, Varian Articles by, (1 of 2 ) (Box 17)
  - Fry, Varian Articles by, (2 of 2 ) (Box 17)
  - Fry, Varian Bibliography of T.S. Eliot (Box 17)
  - Fry, Varian Expulsion from France (Box 17)
  - Fry, Varian "An Innocent Abroad" (Box 17)
  - Fry, Varian Article [draft] on ERC, 1965 (Box 18)
  - Fry, Varian Student Writings (Box 18)
  - Fry, Varian and ERC Articles about (Box 18)
  - Fry, Varian and Gray, Caleb "Take Flight and Follow" (Box 18)
  - Guggenheim (Box 18)
  - Heiden, Konrad (Box 18)
  - Internment Camps (Box 18)
  - Jakob-Sabmon (Box 18)
  - Joint Distribution Committee (Box 18)
  - Lam, Wilfredo (Box 18)
  - Landowska, Wanda (Box 18)
  - Lipchitz, Jacques (Box 18)
  - Matisse, Henri (Box 18)
  - Moore, Henry (Box 18)
  - Neumann, Alfred (Box 18)
  - Picasso, Pablo (Box 18)
  - Refugee Policy, Swiss and British (Box 18)
  - Refugees (Box 18)
  - Refugees, Havens (Box 18)
  - Refugees, Intellectual, Arrival in U.S. (Box 18)
  - Refugees, Intellectual, Austrian (Box 18)
  - Refugees, Spanish (Box 18)
  - Relief Work, United States (Box 18)
  - Riverdale Country Day (Box 18)
  - Comtesse de Rodellec du Porzic (Box 18)
  - Sahl, Hans (Box 18)
  - Strasser, Otto (Box 18)
  - Thyssen, Fritz and Amelia (Box 18)
  - "Transition" (Box 18)
  - Verdet, Andre (Box 18)
  - Vichy (Box 18)
  - Veirny, Dina (Box 18)
  - Visa Policy, United States (Box 18)
  - Wartime Organizations (Box 18)
  - Weiczen, Leo (Box 18)
  - Werfel, Franz (Box 18)
- Series VIII: 2004 Addition
  Foreign Policy Association Headline Books written by Fry or edited by him. Some of these books are bound together in one volume. These books are not available on microfilm.
  - Fry, Varian Bound copies of Foreign Policy Association Headline Books written or edited by Fry collected in one volume. Contains War In China: America's Role in the Far East; The Puzzle of Palestine; Shadow Over Europe: The Challenge of Nazi Germany; Bricks Without Mortar: The Story of International Cooperation; The Good Neighbors: the Story of Two Americas; Battles Without Bullets: The Story of Economic Warfare; In Quest of Empire: The Problem of Colonies; Human Dynamite: The Story of Europe's Minorities; The Peace That Failed: How Europe Sowed the Seeds of War; New Homes for Old: Public Housing in Europe and America., 1938-1940 (Box 19)
  - Fry, Varian War In China: America's Role in The Far East, No. 13, New York, 1938 (Box 19)
  - Fry, Varian Bricks Without Mortar: The Story of International Cooperation, No. 16, New York, 1938, 1939 (Box 19)
  - Fry, Varian The Peace That Failed: How Europe Sowed The Seeds of War, No. 21, New York, 1939 (Box 19)
  - Fry, Varian War Atlas: A Handbook of Maps and Facts, with maps by Emil Herlin, No. 23, New York, 1940 (Box 19)
- Series IX: 2005 Addition
  - Kassof, Anita M.A. Thesis "Intent and Interpretation: The German Refugees and Article 19 of the Franco-German Armistice, 1940-1941", 1992 (Box 19)
  - Varian Fry....du refuge, Hotel du Departement/Marseille, Actes du Colloque, 19 March 1999, (Text in French. ) (Box 19)
  - Varian Fry....a l'exil, Hotel du Department/Marseille, Actes du Colloque, 19 March 1999, (Text in French. ) (Box 19)